In this episode we will have a look at format level 1 from exploit-exercises protostar.
This class of vulnerability is weird, but was mind blowing to me, when I first saw it.
So first of all...
什么是格式字符串？
Probably the most known function in C is printf.
Printf prints formatted data to stdout.
在我的“C编程”视频中，我使用printf打印了一个用户可以打印的名称
supply.
The parameters for printf() are the following.
The first parameter is the so called “format string”.
在早期的视频中，那是“敲门，敲门”。
percentage ‘S’.
And as a second parameter we used argv[1].
Which contains a string.
所以printf读取格式字符串并找到百分比“s”，这意味着
this position belongs a string.
So it takes the first supplied variable, in this case argv[1] and places the string there.
格式字符串支持许多不同类型的变量，例如%d，它
is a signed decimal integer.
Or %x, to display a number in hex.
And you can do even more than that.
例如，如果在百分比和说明符之间指定一个数字，则可以告诉
to what size it should be padded.
And you can for example prepend a 0 to that number, to pad the result with zeroes.
Format string functions like that exist also in other languages.
For example you can use pretty much the same features in python.
Print.
一个格式字符串，包含百分比，然后变量包含另一个百分比。
sign.
Or better use the format function which has a slightly different syntax.
But in the end it’s all the same.
And now you wonder.
怎么能利用那些只打印文本的东西呢？
So let’s have a look at the source code of format level 1.
Main calls the function vuln with the string from argv[1].
And that string is placed in printf.
And then we have a global variable target, which is checked if it got modified.
So pretty similar to the early stack buffer overflow challenges.
We need to manipulate this value.
但是我们如何用printf操作内存中的变量呢？
Well.
Let’s do this step by step.
Let’s first execute the program.
As you can see, it will simply print whatever we supply in argv[1].
That looks simple.
But there is one small thing you should notice.
Which parameter of the printf() does the attacker control?...
It’s not the second parameter like in the programming in C video.
It’s the first parameter.
The format string.
Soooo…
我们能用百分比语法吗？
Let’s try.
Let’s enter a format string.
Test ‘%d’.
Oh damn.
it printed a number.
Weird.
我们再加一点！
Woha. more numbers.
Let’s print them as hex instead of signed decimal numbers.
That looks more familiar.
还记得我们在看堆栈的视频吗？
这些以bfff开头的值是否提醒了您一些事情？
Those were stack addresses.
那么我们在这里打印什么？
如果你看过前一集关于反转c的内容，你就知道函数是如何工作的。
called.
Especially in 32bit.
The parameters are simply placed on to the stack, and then the function is called.
因此，如果您通常使用printf，那么您想要打印的变量将是
placed on the stack.
好吧，现在没有变量放在堆栈上，那么您要读取什么值呢？
Obviously you are reading whatever printf can find on the stack.
So any value on the stack.
那你能用它做什么呢？
First of all, it is a memory leak vulnerability.
You can leak all kinds of stuff from the stack.
假设您有一个带有aslr的程序，这意味着堆栈在内存中的位置是
random.
你不知道它在哪里，但是你需要一个缓冲区溢出的地址
jump to shellcode.
在这里，您可以从进程内存中泄漏值，更具体地说是从
stack, and thus possibly leaking stack addresses.
Which can then be used in a second step for a buffer overflow.
在我最近玩的CTF中，有一个可利用的挑战，我使用了一种格式
string vulnerability to leak the stack canary.
我将在另一个地方做一个关于漏洞缓解的视频，但是堆栈金丝雀是
a random value which protects from buffer overflows.
If I can get this number, I can defeat this protection.
Which I did.
所以一开始从进程内存中泄漏一些奇怪的值听上去不太像，
但是有很多例子你可以想出，在那里透露一些记忆可以
help exploiting a target.
After all, bugs like heartbleed were “just” leaking some memory and it was awful.
Ok but in our particular case.
How can we use that to modify a value.
At the moment it only looks like we can leak values from the stack.
Let’s have a look at the printf manpage.
man 3 printf.
And let’s scroll to the well known BUGS section.
它在这里说，“如果某些东西来自不受信任的用户
输入，它可能包含%n，导致printf（）调用写入内存并创建安全性
孔”和更进一步的说明符
“n”解释为：
n到目前为止写入的字符数存储在整数中，该整数由
int * (or variant) pointer argument.
所以百分比“n”将已经打印的字符量写入
a variable.
And a variable is just some area in memory.
And we know that to specify where that area is, we need use a pointer.
或者，如果我们只看汇编程序代码，指针只是一个地址，所以printf
knows where to write the result.
因此，如果您要用%n编写一个合法的C程序，您将放置一个指向整数的指针
变量作为printf的参数，或者在汇编程序中，只需将
the variable onto the stack.
这意味着，无论堆栈上的值是什么，都将用作printf的位置
will write to.
Now you can basically solve this challenge alone.
We need to write a value in target.
So let’s use objdump -t to find all symbols from this binary.
And here is the address of the target variable.
现在，当我们希望printf在这个位置写东西时，我们必须找到这个地址
on the stack.
Let’s start investigating.
我将使用python和命令行via-c中的一行脚本来帮助我
printing a test string.
For example 10 hex numbers.
Mh.
Maybe I want to seperate them.
Doesn’t look like the address is here.
Maybe if we print more values from the stack.
Nope.
Not here.
也许更多？
Wait a minute.
What is that weird pattern.
From the values of those hex values it could be ascii.
hex 20 is a space afterall.
With python we can quickly convert those hex values to a ascii characters.
And wooohh..
%x？
That loooks like our string that we have supplied.
Let’s test that.
Let’s add some capital As, because we can recognize those ascii values easily.
Now we just have to look for 4141414141.
And indeed.
there are our As.
And that makes sense.
因为程序参数只存储在堆栈上，就像环境变量一样
and other stuff.
Cool.
这意味着我们可以通过
adding it to our string.
So get the address again for target, and then we can add the address in our string.
Maybe wrap it in some As and Bs, so we can find it in the output easily.
Uhhh. yes.
There it is.
酷！
所以理论上，我们只需要用%n替换打印此地址的%x
改为写这个
address location.
You could do it more intelligently, but I will just figure it out with trial and error.
你必须小心，因为请记住我们以前的视频中堆栈移动的地方
因为环境变量之类的东西？
The different length program argument that we supply, moves around the stack as well.
So you might have to fiddle around quite a bit until you just get it right.
Ok that took a bit, but looks cool.
The last %x seems to reference our address now.
And when we replace the x with the n, to write to that address we modified the target.
你可以想象，如果我们能在记忆中的任何地方写，我们就能改写一些东西。
to redirect code execution as well.
So that will be the case in later levels.
Just a small tip for when you work on format string exploits.
It makes sense to keep your attack string always the same length.
Then you don’t have to fiddle around much.
只需使用一个python脚本，它总是以500个字符的长度扩展或剪切字符串。
or something.
And then you have enough space to play around and the stack doesn’t move around.